A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Neighborhood Security and Crime Unit, Office Files of Sharon Rowser and Craig Howard FA1621
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Urban Poverty Program, Neighborhood Security and Crime Unit, Office Files of Sharon Rowser and Craig Howard
1973-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Rowser, Sharon L.
Howard, Craig
FA1621
2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document containers
Scope and Contents
The collection is primarily comprised of grant materials and reports related to the Ford Foundation's crime and arson prevention program to investigate the impact of street crime, arson, and violence across the country. The files in this collection are the office files of Sharon Rowser and Craig Howard, program officers in the Urban Poverty program at the Ford Foundation.
Biographical / Historical
In 1981, the Ford Foundation began funding efforts to prevent crime and arson in urban communities. This Neighborhood Security and Crime Prevention initiative arose in response to the increase in the national crime rate in the 1960s and '70s. The program coincided with Ford Foundation president Franklin Thomas's efforts to reorganize Foundation priorities in 1981. Thomas championed the program by noting the Foundation's community development and neighborhood development efforts were being undermined by crime and arson in urban areas. Prior to 1980, the Foundation was not focused specifically on community crime prevention efforts, but grants were made in areas of law and justice (litigation, administration of justice, legal education and minority professional development, conflict resolution, and policing methods). During this time, the most significant law and justice Ford grants went to criminal justice study centers at the University of Chicago, Georgetown University, Harvard University and the University of California at Berkeley and Davis. The Ford Foundation also established the Police Foundation in 1970 with a five-year, $30 million grant.
The 1982 report "Neighborhood security and crime prevention (Reports 006623)" outlined the plans for the program. The Foundation would provide grants to existing, underfunded organizations focused on crime prevention, test effective models through demonstration projects and evaluations, and provide funds for public policy research. The Foundation's goals were to examine the impact of crimes and violence on community members and local businesses, provide grants to innovative crime prevention strategies in cities, focus on youth training initiatives, and work to strengthen the social fabric of low-income neighborhoods. The program was housed within the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty program. Between 1983 and 1987, grantees included the National Fire Protection Association, the American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences, the COSMOS Corporation, the People's Firehouse and the Flatbush Development Corporation in Brooklyn, the Citizens Information Service of Illinois, Community Crime Prevention in Minneapolis, the Eisenhower Foundation for the Prevention of Violence in Washington, D.C., the Justice Resource Center in Boston, the Boston-Fenway Program, the Citizens Committee for New York City, the National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives (NOBLE), the Chicago Alliance for Neighborhood Safety, the Vera Institute of Justice, The Police Foundation, and the Police Executive Research Forum. The Foundation continued funding crime and arson prevention work after 1987, but the grants were integrated into community development activities. There was no longer a standalone program.
The program officers who oversaw the disbursement of crime prevention grants within the Ford Foundation's Urban Poverty program were Sharon Rowser (1981-1985) and Craig Howard (1986-1987).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:106 (Boxes 38737 and 38738).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series: Series 1. Grants and Reports, 1973-1992
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arson -- Prevention; Crime prevention; Community development; Ford Foundation; Neighborhood revitalization -- United States; Violence -- Prevention
- Grants and Reports, 1973-1992; 1; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  - Arson Prediction and Prevention: A Guide for Community Organizations, Royer Cook, Janice Roehl, and Adele Harrell, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Predicting and Preventing Arson: An Evaluation of Community-Based Strategies, Executive Summary, Royer Cook, Janice Roehl, and Adele Harrell, 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Neighborhood Based Arson Control: A Guide to Citizen-Initiated Legal Remedies, Battelle Human Affairs Research Centers, Washington, D.C. with the Citizens Committee for Fire Protection Washington, D.C., 1983 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Police Executive Research Forum - Grants, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Police Executive Research Forum - Extras (Newsletters, Pamphlets, Etc.), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Police Foundation - Grants, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    Scope and Contents
    Ford Foundation Grants 07100114, 08550448
  - Police Foundation: An Evaluation, Project Evaluation (C-55), National Affairs Division, Ford Foundation, 1977 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A Proposal to Establish a Permanent Police Foundation Endowment, Submitted to the Ford Foundation, 1987 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clipping - Crime Expert Foresees Temporary Crime Decline, 1984 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Police Foundation - Progress Reports, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14, Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Police Foundation - Minority Pipeline - $25,000 Delegated Authority Grant, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Police Foundation - Grants, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Police Foundation - Grants and Memos, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Police Foundation: An Assessment of the Last Five Years and a Look to the Future, Urban and Rural Poverty Committee - Information Paper, 1983 December (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Police Foundation - Extras, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - An Assessment of the Vera Institute of Justice by William Grinker with Gary Walker, 1984 February (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Grants and paper - Employment, Youth, and Violent Crime by Michael Smith and James W. Thomas, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Vera Institue of Justice - Grants and Reports, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Grant #06600329, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Grants and Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Mission Statement, 1985 January 31 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Grants (For Signature), 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Vera Institute of Justice - Grants and Correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Vocational Foundation - Grant #08550864, 1985 August (Box 3, Folder 29)
    $50,000 two years beginning July 1, 1985
  - Wolfson College, Cambridge - Grant, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    One year beginning January 1, 1987
  - Criminal Justice Grants - Program Action Forms, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Criminal Justice Grants - Program Action Forms (Formerly Closed Grants), 1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Criminal Justice Publications, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Monograph, Residential Security, U.S. Department of Justice, Law Enforcement Assistance Administration, National Institute of Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice
    Law and Justice (Ford publication)
    ...and Justice for All (Ford booklet)
  - Criminal Justice Delegated Authority Grants - Extras, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences - Grant Action Form, 1985 January (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Grant No. 830-0578
  - American Institutes for Research - Grant #08350427, 1983 April (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Boston-Fenway Program - Grant Action Form, 1985 November (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Community Boards Monitoring File - Grant Forms and Reports, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Grants to Community Board Program, San Francisco and Citizens Committee for New York City
  - COSMOS Corporation - Neighborhood AIMS Project, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Conference Papers and Reports, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Cranfield - "Crime and Social Strategies in Local Communities of Europe", papers submitted for the proposed September conference 1985, Centre for Policy Studies in Social Order
    Neighborhood AIMS Project: Interim Report of Accomplishments, June 1985
    People Who Have Struggled with Abortion: A Proposal for a Program in the Are You Listening series
  - Children's Defense Fund - Grant Action Form, 1984 August (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Justice Resource Institute - Grant #08200962, 1985 February (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Metropolitan Assistance Corporation (formerly Victim Services, Inc.) Grant #08250674 and Extras, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
  - National Fire Protection - Grant #08300578, 1985 January (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives (NOBLE) - Grant #08400727, Amount $145,500, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives (NOBLE) - Extras, 1984 August (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - People's Firehouse - Grant Action Forms, 1984-1988 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Philadelphia Miniversity - Extras, 1984 August (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Planned Parenthood Grant #08100052, 1985 January (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Urban Educational Systems - Extras, 1985 June (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Women and Foundations/Corporate Philanthropy - Grant #08290203, 1982 June (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Community Development Corporations (CDCs)/Local Development Corporations (LDCs) in New York City - Correspondence and Report, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Completed Criminal Justice Grants, 1982-1988 (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
    Folder 54: List of Grantees A-N
    The ACLU Foundation of Georgia (08650080)
    American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Science (08300578)
    Battelle Memorial Institute (08550205)
    Chicago Alliance for Neighborhood Safety (08500875)
    Citizens Committee for New York City (08400674) (08750750) (08400647)
    Children's Defense Fund (08400729)
    COSMOS Corporation (08300579)
    Cranfield Institute of Technology (08350167)
    Eisenhower Foundation for the Prevention of Violence (08200703) (08550979)
    The Flatbush Development Corporation (08200874)
    Institute for Social Analysis (08550815)
    John Jay of Criminal Justice (08550765)
    Martha Stuart Communications (08300825)
    Metropolitan Assistance (Victim Services/Travelers Aid) Corporation (08700143)
    National Association of Town Watch (08750183) (08550914)
    National Firehawk Foundation (08650077)
    National Fire Protection Association (08300577)
    National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives (NOBLE) (08700348) (08400727)
    Folder 55: List of Grantees O-Z
    The People's Firehouse (08700350) (08200875)
    The Philadelphia Miniversity (08700349) (08400728)
    Planned Parenthood of New York City (08100052)
    Police Athletic League (08550879)
    Police Executive Research Forum (08400084) (08550736) (08450963)
    Police Foundation (08750168) (08550448) (07100114)
    Syracuse University (08251185)
    United States Conference of Mayors (08550698)
    Urban Educational Systems (08500695)
    Vera Institute of Justice (08600477) (06600329) (08300984)
    Vocational Foundation (08550864)
    Wolfson College (08750122)
  - Grants Made By Craig Howard, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 56-58)